<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>coroutines on Jacques Smuts</title>
        <link>https://jacquessmuts.github.io/tags/coroutines/</link>
        <description>Recent content in coroutines on Jacques Smuts</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <copyright>© This post is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License，please give source if you wish to quote or reproduce.</copyright>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 02 Jun 2019 09:08:10 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://jacquessmuts.github.io/tags/coroutines/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
        <title>Using the synchronized keyword in coroutines?</title>
        <link>https://jacquessmuts.github.io/post/coroutine_sync_mutex/</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jun 2019 09:08:10 +0200</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://jacquessmuts.github.io/post/coroutine_sync_mutex/</guid>
        <description>&lt;img src="https://jacquessmuts.github.io/images/coroutine_sync_mutex.png" alt="Featured image of post Using the synchronized keyword in coroutines?" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Working with coroutines is subtly different from normal locking functions. Introduce some thread-safety with mutex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;thread-safety-normally&#34;&gt;Thread-Safety, normally&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So hopefully you&amp;rsquo;re aware of basic thread-safety in Kotlin/Java. Sometimes you have a shared state of some kind that should only be accessed by one thread at a time. If you&amp;rsquo;re coming from Java, you probably use the &lt;code&gt;synchronized(lock)&lt;/code&gt; operator in order to ensure that a shared mutable object can only be accessed one at a time. For some great reading on this topic I suggest &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://proandroiddev.com/synchronization-and-thread-safety-techniques-in-java-and-kotlin-f63506370e6d&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;this post on Medium&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;so-imagine-a-scenario-where-we-are-running-a-few-long-running-operations-like-api-calls-but-we-want-to-make-sure-that-we-never-run-more-than-one-such-operation-at-a-time&#34;&gt;So imagine a scenario where we are running a few long-running operations (like API calls), but we want to make sure that we never run more than one such operation at a time.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was starting out with Java threading I&amp;rsquo;d probably write something risky like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;kotlin-code&#34;
     
        data-target-platform=&#34;java&#34;
    
     &gt;
    &lt;pre&gt;
        &lt;code class=&#34;hljs language-kotlin&#34;&gt;
        
import kotlinx.coroutines.GlobalScope
import kotlinx.coroutines.launch

fun main() {

    val lockClass = SyncLockClass()
    for (i in 1..10) {
        GlobalScope.launch { lockClass.runFunction(i) }
    }

    Thread.sleep(2000) // We&amp;#39;re sleeping here because otherwise the JVM would terminate before printing the results
}

class SyncLockClass() {
	val lock = Any()
	var latestValue: Int = 0

//sampleStart
	fun runFunction(input: Int) {
        println(&amp;#34;start function $input&amp;#34;)
	    [mark]synchronized(lock) {[/mark]
	        Thread.sleep(100) // This could also be a long-running calculation or an API call
	        latestValue = input
	    }
	    println(&amp;#34;finished function $input at ${System.currentTimeMillis()}&amp;#34;)
	}
//sampleEnd

	companion object {
		// Put the sync lock inside a companion object if you want to ensure that all instances of this class share a lock
		// val lock = Any()
	}
}

        &lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Press the play button above (assuming you didn&amp;rsquo;t block JavaScript on this page) to see the result. Each function is blocked and waits at the &lt;code&gt;synchronized&lt;/code&gt; keyword for the previous function to finish. This mostly satisfies our initial requirement, but blocks any thread which hits the &lt;code&gt;synchronized&lt;/code&gt; section while it is locked. Notice how once the first few functions are hit, the JVM is blocked from starting new threads until the previous thread finishes. In other words this method works (but is dangerous) if you have lots of threads and are running blocking functions. In Kotlin Coroutines however we run &lt;code&gt;suspending&lt;/code&gt; functions, not blocking functions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;badly-with-coroutines&#34;&gt;Badly, with Coroutines&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re already using coroutines you should know that a suspending function does not always block a thread. In some circumstances it pauses (suspends) the operation so that other operations can use the CPU.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the example above, I&amp;rsquo;m using coroutines to launch the function, but I&amp;rsquo;m still blocking the thread every time the &lt;code&gt;runFunction()&lt;/code&gt; function is performed, which means I&amp;rsquo;m not really utilizing the full power of Kotlin coroutines. So, what if we replaced the blocking &lt;code&gt;Sleep&lt;/code&gt; function with the suspending &lt;code&gt;delay()&lt;/code&gt; function?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;kotlin-code&#34;
     
        data-target-platform=&#34;java&#34;
    
     &gt;
    &lt;pre&gt;
        &lt;code class=&#34;hljs language-kotlin&#34;&gt;
        
import kotlinx.coroutines.GlobalScope
import kotlinx.coroutines.launch
import kotlinx.coroutines.delay

fun main() {

    val lockClass = SyncLockClass()

    for (i in 1..10) {
        GlobalScope.launch { lockClass.runFunction(i) }
    }

    Thread.sleep(2000) // We&amp;#39;re sleeping here because otherwise the JVM would terminate before printing the results
}

class SyncLockClass() {
	val lock = Any()
	var latestValue: Int = 0

//sampleStart
	suspend fun runFunction(input: Int) {
        println(&amp;#34;start function $input&amp;#34;)
	    synchronized(lock) {
	        [mark]delay(100)[/mark] // This could also be a long-running calculation or an API call
	        latestValue = input
	    }
	    println(&amp;#34;finished function $input at ${System.currentTimeMillis()}&amp;#34;)
	}
//sampleEnd
}


        &lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try to run the above code and you&amp;rsquo;ll get an error: &lt;code&gt;The &#39;delay&#39; suspension point is inside a critical section&lt;/code&gt;. What does this mean? You should not delay or suspend or sleep your thread inside of a synchronized() block, as explained somewhat &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://stackoverflow.com/questions/4160413/why-is-sleeping-inside-a-critical-section-a-concurrency-issue&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;in this StackOverflow Thread&lt;/a&gt;. It would ideally display as a warning in my first example as well. A critical section of code (such as in between the &lt;code&gt;synchronized&lt;/code&gt; block) should be as short as possible. It is not for long-running operations because it blocks the thread. But a suspending function does not necessarily block the thread.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how do we solve this issue? Maybe you&amp;rsquo;re an oldschool Java dev and you think to just use ReentrantLock() instead. After all, synchronized is merely a simplified version of ReentrantLock. This is cheating to try and be smarter than the compiler. Don&amp;rsquo;t do this. Run the code below to see why.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;kotlin-code&#34;
     
        data-target-platform=&#34;java&#34;
    
     &gt;
    &lt;pre&gt;
        &lt;code class=&#34;hljs language-kotlin&#34;&gt;
        
import kotlinx.coroutines.GlobalScope
import kotlinx.coroutines.launch
import kotlinx.coroutines.delay
import java.util.concurrent.locks.ReentrantLock

fun main() {

    val lockClass = SyncLockClass()

	for (i in 1..10) {
        GlobalScope.launch { lockClass.runFunction(i) }
    }

    Thread.sleep(2000) // We&amp;#39;re sleeping here because otherwise the JVM would terminate before printing the results
}

class SyncLockClass() {
    val reentrantLock = ReentrantLock()
	var latestValue: Int = 0

//sampleStart
	suspend fun runFunction(input: Int) {
        println(&amp;#34;start function $input&amp;#34;)
        reentrantLock.lock()
	    [mark]delay(100)[/mark] // This could also be a long-running calculation or an API call
	    latestValue = input
	    reentrantLock.unlock()
	    println(&amp;#34;finished function $input at ${System.currentTimeMillis()}&amp;#34;)
	}
//sampleEnd
}

        &lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see this is not the results we want at all. The lock breaks, and then it gets ignored. You&amp;rsquo;ll probably have a runtime error in the log as well. So how do we fix this? We use a Mutex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;coroutinessyncmutex&#34;&gt;Coroutines.Sync.Mutex&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are some things we can read online on Mutex. We&amp;rsquo;ve got &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://kotlin.github.io/kotlinx.coroutines/kotlinx-coroutines-core/kotlinx.coroutines.sync/-mutex/index.html&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;the class documentation&lt;/a&gt;, we have this nice &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://medium.com/@nazarivanchuk/shared-mutable-state-with-coroutines-33a85e903466&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;acricte&lt;/a&gt; which explains how to use the mutex with a shared mutable state, and finally we have the &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://kotlinlang.org/docs/reference/coroutines/shared-mutable-state-and-concurrency.html#mutual-exclusion&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;official kotlin guide&lt;/a&gt;. That last link is probably the best one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The important takeaway is that the Mutex is part of the Coroutines package, which means we know that this mutex takes the suspending nature of coroutines into account. So how would we use it in our example?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;kotlin-code&#34;
     
        data-target-platform=&#34;java&#34;
    
     &gt;
    &lt;pre&gt;
        &lt;code class=&#34;hljs language-kotlin&#34;&gt;
        
import kotlinx.coroutines.GlobalScope
import kotlinx.coroutines.launch
import kotlinx.coroutines.delay
import kotlinx.coroutines.sync.Mutex
import kotlinx.coroutines.sync.withLock

fun main() {

    val lockClass = SyncLockClass()

	for (i in 1..10) {
        GlobalScope.launch { lockClass.runSuspendFunctionWithMutex(i) }
    }

    Thread.sleep(2000) // We&amp;#39;re sleeping here because otherwise the JVM would terminate before printing the results
}

class SyncLockClass() {
	var latestValue: Int = 0
	val mutex = Mutex()

	//sampleStart
	suspend fun runSuspendFunctionWithMutex(input: Int) {

    	println(&amp;#34;running suspend function $input&amp;#34;)
	    [mark]mutex.withLock { [/mark]
	    	delay(100) // This could also be a long-running calculation or an API call
	        println(&amp;#34;finished suspend function $input at ${System.currentTimeMillis()}&amp;#34;)
	        latestValue = input
	    }

}
//sampleEnd
}

        &lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And now things are working fine. All of the API calls are started as soon as possible and none of the threads are locked. If you look at the timestamps of the logs above you&amp;rsquo;ll see that the events are also returned with the expected 100ms delay in between each one. The only way to have achieved this result using the same techniques as in the first example is to have 10 threads at your disposal. In fact, I can probably increase the amount of coroutines I launch with this method. Let&amp;rsquo;s push it until we break it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;kotlin-code&#34;
     
        data-target-platform=&#34;java&#34;
    
     &gt;
    &lt;pre&gt;
        &lt;code class=&#34;hljs language-kotlin&#34;&gt;
        
import kotlinx.coroutines.GlobalScope
import kotlinx.coroutines.launch
import kotlinx.coroutines.delay
import kotlinx.coroutines.sync.Mutex
import kotlinx.coroutines.sync.withLock

fun main() {

    val lockClass = SyncLockClass()

    println(&amp;#34;(only printing the first 3, and multiples of 50)&amp;#34;)
	//sampleStart
	for (i in 1..4000) {
        GlobalScope.launch { lockClass.runSuspendFunctionWithMutex(i) }
    }

    Thread.sleep(8000) // We&amp;#39;re sleeping here because otherwise the JVM would terminate before printing the results
	//sampleEnd
}

class SyncLockClass() {
	var latestValue: Int = 0
	val mutex = Mutex()

	suspend fun runSuspendFunctionWithMutex(input: Int) {

		if (input &amp;lt; 4 || input % 50 == 0)
    		println(&amp;#34;running suspend function $input&amp;#34;)
	    mutex.withLock {
	    	delay(2) // This could also be a long-running calculation or an API call

			if (input &amp;lt; 4 || input % 50 == 0)
	        	println(&amp;#34;finished suspend function $input at ${System.currentTimeMillis()}&amp;#34;)
	        latestValue = input
	    }

}
}

        &lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t manage to break the Kotlin Playground with any amount of coroutines. The environment provided by the Kotlin playground only allows you to run for 10 seconds. The above code maximises that time without breaking anything, or blocking any threads. If you scroll through the logs you&amp;rsquo;ll see that some of the old functions are eventually getting finished while more coroutines are still being launched. This just goes to show how powerful coroutines and suspending functions are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-better-way&#34;&gt;A Better way?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Threading and concurrency is a difficult topic. It is exceptionally easy to shoot yourself in the foot, by for example creating a deadlock. I suggest you read &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://medium.com/@elizarov/deadlocks-in-non-hierarchical-csp-e5910d137cc&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;this great article by Roman Elizarov&lt;/a&gt; on how to avoid deadlocks in practical coroutines. (Thanks to &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://github.com/spand&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;Johannes Jensen&lt;/a&gt; for the suggestion.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our code sample above works, but it&amp;rsquo;s still dangerous. If one function gets locked or indefinitely suspended for any reason, you end up in a deadlock. Ideally you want to avoid launching a coroutine or entering a suspend function until the conditions are ideal to do so. If you cannot stop a coroutine from being launched when it&amp;rsquo;s not ready, you can at least queue up several suspend functions using the &lt;code&gt;Mutex&lt;/code&gt; class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But since we&amp;rsquo;re queuing things up, maybe it would be better to use something like the &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://docs.oracle.com/javase/8/docs/api/?java/util/concurrent/BlockingQueue.html&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;BlockingQueue&lt;/a&gt; class in Java? I&amp;rsquo;m still investigating that part, but spoilers: &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://kotlinlang.org/docs/reference/coroutines/channels.html#channel-basics&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;Channels&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coroutines are better than multithreading, but comes with all of the same dangers as normal multithreading. Just because it&amp;rsquo;s easy to use does not mean it&amp;rsquo;s safe. Be careful out there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can you think of a better way to handle this scenario? Please let me know in the comments below.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Escaping Callback Hell with Generic SuspendCoroutine Infix Extension Functions</title>
        <link>https://jacquessmuts.github.io/post/callback-hell/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 20 May 2019 23:12:36 +0200</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://jacquessmuts.github.io/post/callback-hell/</guid>
        <description>&lt;img src="https://jacquessmuts.github.io/images/callback_hell4.png" alt="Featured image of post Escaping Callback Hell with Generic SuspendCoroutine Infix Extension Functions" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Callback hell happens all the time in Android. Luckily, with coroutines, there&amp;rsquo;s an easy way out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So you&amp;rsquo;re hopefully aware of &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;http://callbackhell.com/&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;callback hell&lt;/a&gt;, which makes your code difficult to read, and also makes the sequence of events difficult to understand. This is something we want to avoid, but it&amp;rsquo;s not always easy. If you&amp;rsquo;re using any sort of third-party library, (like Firebase) you&amp;rsquo;re probably forced into this pattern regularly. A simple callback would look like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;application/javascript&#34; src=&#34;https://gist.github.com/JacquesSmuts/6cdad47d20e6c4f2a92ebee4f1ff8640.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, we&amp;rsquo;re one level into callbacks. At a glance, it would seem like the result would be handled immediately after sending out the &lt;code&gt;saveUsername&lt;/code&gt; function. But it in fact creates an asynchronous task (most likely on the IO thread). Which means the order of events quickly becomes unclear, especially to a new developer climbing on the project. An experienced dev would know that the order of events isn&amp;rsquo;t clear, but it&amp;rsquo;ll take a few minutes to fully comprehend what the actual order is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, if your operation is suitable for coroutines (such as API calls, disk writes or background processes) we can &amp;ldquo;flatten&amp;rdquo; the callback hell fairly easily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;suspendcoroutine&#34;&gt;SuspendCoroutine&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m assuming you&amp;rsquo;re aware of coroutines and suspendFunctions already. If not, it&amp;rsquo;s time to &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://kotlinlang.org/docs/reference/coroutines-overview.html&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;start using them&lt;/a&gt;. First, I need to introduce suspendCoroutine. The &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://kotlinlang.org/api/latest/jvm/stdlib/kotlin.coroutines.experimental/suspend-coroutine.html&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;official documentation on suspendCoroutine&lt;/a&gt; doesn&amp;rsquo;t make it particularly clear. But &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://stackoverflow.com/questions/50315802/correct-way-to-suspend-coroutine-until-taskt-is-complete&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;this StackOverflow answer&lt;/a&gt; provides a good idea of how to use it. So if we were to write a suspendCoroutine version of our function, it would look like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;application/javascript&#34; src=&#34;https://gist.github.com/JacquesSmuts/40462adab3f657da91d25dfdba84ef99.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, the saveUsername function has turned into a function which returns the result in the same line, but can only be called from a coroutineContext/suspendFunction. This is perfect for making your code look cleaner and run in sequence with more confidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, it requires you to write a suspendCoroutine function for each function you want to flatten in this way. This adds a lot of boilerplate. So is there some way we can use generics to avoid this boilerplate? Of course!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;generic-suspendcoroutine&#34;&gt;Generic SuspendCoroutine&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you read my &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://jacquessmuts.github.io/post/generic_interface_and_methods/&#34; &gt;first article on kotlin generics&lt;/a&gt; you&amp;rsquo;ll know that the IntelliJ IDE is smarter than us, so we&amp;rsquo;ll use it to generate our function. We&amp;rsquo;ll call our function &lt;code&gt;suspendAsync()&lt;/code&gt; and pass in our method, along with the input, and see what happens. Remember you can pass a method reference with &lt;code&gt;instance::method&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&#34;zoomable&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://jacquessmuts.github.io/images/callback_hell1.png&#34;
         alt=&#34;compiler error&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34;/&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;h4&gt;If you see this warning, you&amp;#39;re headed in the right direction. &lt;/h4&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then IntelliJ creates a function which looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&#34;zoomable&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://jacquessmuts.github.io/images/callback_hell2.png&#34;
         alt=&#34;compiler result&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34;/&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;h4&gt;Not generic yet. &lt;/h4&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And through a little bit of Generic reworking, as well as &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://jacquessmuts.github.io/post/kfunction_analogues/&#34; &gt;my knowledge of KFunction analogues&lt;/a&gt;, I replaced the &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;String&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; input and output types with generic types, resulting in this function:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;application/javascript&#34; src=&#34;https://gist.github.com/JacquesSmuts/8ae63a3da81d38708c0c35a300280a86.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, it&amp;rsquo;s about the same as our previous function. The difference is, you can pass in any function which takes a single input and a function callback, and it becomes a one-liner instead of a callback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to pass in two inputs, it&amp;rsquo;s slightly trickier, but still very doable:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;application/javascript&#34; src=&#34;https://gist.github.com/JacquesSmuts/9d1c10544e72c4d88e978ca65c5f07ff.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there you have it. You can reduce any qualifying callback with these functions. Other variations can be covered with a few more generic functions. However, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t feel very nice calling a function in this way. First you write &lt;code&gt;suspendAsync&lt;/code&gt;, then you pass in the function you actually want to call? Not the best, because we&amp;rsquo;re used to referencing the function we want to call first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So maybe we can do better?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;generic-infix-suspendcoroutine-extension-function&#34;&gt;Generic Infix SuspendCoroutine Extension Function&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like the &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://kotlinlang.org/docs/reference/functions.html#infix-notation&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;infix notation in Kotlin&lt;/a&gt;, though I usually avoid it because it&amp;rsquo;s a little dangerous and it&amp;rsquo;s not easy for new developers to discover it&amp;rsquo;s usage in any given codebase. In this case the increased readability and ease of use may be worth it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So using the same method of letting the IDE generate our function for us, we write out the infix function we want. I call it &lt;code&gt;suspendAndInvokeWith&lt;/code&gt;, because we are invoking a function, turning it into a suspend function, and passing in arguments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&#34;zoomable&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://jacquessmuts.github.io/images/callback_hell3.png&#34;
         alt=&#34;compiler result&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34;/&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;h4&gt;If it wasn&amp;#39;t for compiler suggestions I&amp;#39;d be useless. &lt;/h4&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which we clean up and genericify a little bit into our result:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;application/javascript&#34; src=&#34;https://gist.github.com/JacquesSmuts/d099eff5e66aa6b1d5de924f87c9e967.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This feels a lot more natural. You start out by writing the function you would normally write, using the infix notation and passing in your input.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Infix functions require only a single input, so if you want to pass in more than one argument into a function, you need to do it by using Pairs or Triples, like so:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;application/javascript&#34; src=&#34;https://gist.github.com/JacquesSmuts/b6b45f506d001005bc8914e0925986cc.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there you have it. This won&amp;rsquo;t work on everything, but it&amp;rsquo;s a start to reducing boilerplate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;source&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://flatcircle.io/&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;Flat Circle&lt;/a&gt;, we&amp;rsquo;re trying to make our code as readable as possible, and found that using coroutines and avoiding callback hell is a good way to go about doing this. So we built these infix notations (and a few other utility functions) into a little &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://github.com/flatcircle/coroutinehelper&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;CoroutineHelper Library&lt;/a&gt; to make our lives easier. Please go ahead and use that library or copy the code to help make your code as readable as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Callback hell isn&amp;rsquo;t the end of the world, but sometimes it can add just a little bit too much confusion to an already complex lifecycle. Hopefully with Coroutines, coupled with the techniques and Generic Utility functions above, you can reduce callback hell a little bit in your code.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
